So, lets go on with our development.
In this issue we'll have a look at the most typical thing one can do with two branches - merge them.
The "fix" branch was made previously to fix the mistakes of the "master" branch.
Now this fix is finished.
Im going to add the changes that we've made there in our main branch "master".
To make it, let's switch to it at first: "git checkout master".
We want to add changes from the "fix" branch here.
For that theres a "git merge" command in git, which does, as you've probably guessed, the merge.
This commands has a lot of possibilities and arguements.
Right now we are looking at the most basic way to use it, and we'll get to a more advanced ones later.
Specify from what branch the changes are to be added, in our case from the "fix".
Done. As we can see in the editor, changes that were done on in the "fix" are now in our "master" branch.
Lets read the output of the merge command, it describes what have happened.
For better visualisation, lets temporary revert the image on the right to the before the merge state.
The first lane shows what was merged with what.
This commit was the tip of the "master" branch and this commit was the last on the "fix" branch.
Next line contains the name of the algorithm, used to perform the merge.
Thats the way in which git will add changes from fix to master.
Fast forward is one of the very simple algorithms.
Its quite remarkable by the fact that it doesnt add the changes from fix to master, but the other way around,
master's pointer is moved so that it points to the same commit as fix does.
In other words, here was the "master" branch, how to add new changes from fix to it?
Just move the corresponding pointer forward, thats it, and the new commits are already in master.
As now master and fix are pointing to the same commit, see, Im making a checkout and nothing changes.
Lets assume that we have a sudden change of a heart as fix had some issues and we want to revert the master to its previous state.
No problem, git has a lot of ways to roll back the changes and make it exactly as it was.
In this case we can use the command that we've already seen: "git branch -f".
Lets use it to move the "master" branch back.
However, in real life we dont remember the commit identifier, at which the "master" branch was previously.
The commit identifiers are not something that people usually rememeber.
Fortunately, git has our back covered for this case.
The merge command before moving the branch writes the old identifier to the ".git/ORIG_HEAD" file.
And we can use it as a "git branch -f master ORIG_HEAD" - moves the master back to ORIG_HEAD.
Done, master was reverted.
We dont see any changes in the editor now.
Thats because we are on the "fix" branch and branch command have changed the "master" branch only.
But if we switch to it, then, really heres the previous state of the project. Everything as it was before.
Lets try to move the branch back: "git branch -f master", let it point to the same place as fix.
Error. Git branch cant move the branch at which we currently are.
We can leave it or use the "checkout" command for the move which is less picky.
I remind you that the "b" flag creates a branch with the name provided pointing to the current commit.
And then, when the branch is created it switches to it.
And if the branch already exists it's moved.
As Im in the "master" branch already, theres no switch only the branch was moved.
In the end we get the same result,
as after calling the "git merge" command, but you see, by using the "checkout" command.
This is, of course in this particular case, and mostly merge is a more powerfull command.
Here we only needed to move the branch to add the changes from the fix to the master.
A more complex case is going to be examined in one of the later issues.